Finding Aid for James B. Griffin Papers 1922-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James B. Griffin papers
1922-1997
Griffin, James Bennett, 1905-1997
James Bennett Griffin was one of the major forces in the development of North American archaeology and served as the director of the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan from 1946 to 1975. The papers contain correspondence, extensive research and photograph files on North American archaeological sites, cultures and artifacts, and information on Griffin's writing, professional activities, and teaching within the University of Michigan Department of Anthropology.
0313 Aa 2
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
216 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers (donor no. 9273 ) were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library in 2002.
The papers are open without restriction.
In 2013 select materials were returned to the University Michigan Museum of Anthropology. This includes part or all of boxes 83, 84 and 86-93. These files are available for use at the Museum of Anthropology.
James ("Jimmy") Bennett Griffin was one of the major forces in the development of North American archaeology. In his long, productive, and highly distinguished career spanning nearly seven decades, he played a pivotal role in transforming American archaeology into a fully scientific discipline.
James B. Griffin was born in Atchison, Kansas on January 12, 1905. His father's occupation as a railroad man moved his family from Kansas to Denver to Oak Park, Illinois during Griffin's childhood. Griffin entered the University of Chicago in 1923 for undergraduate study. He initially pursued a course in business administration, then law, but eventually settled on a social science major. His studies exposed him to introductory anthropology and ethnology courses, including one taught by Fay-Cooper Cole, and engendered a lifelong fascination with human origins and cultural development.
Griffin received his bachelor's degree from Chicago in 1927, but with his father ill and his family in need of financial support, he decided to enter a training program to become a junior executive for Standard Oil of Indiana. He manned service stations in the Chicago area for about a year and a half, but quickly lost interest in a career in business. In 1928, Griffin abandoned business permanently and returned to the University of Chicago to pursue a master's degree in anthropology under Cole. While in the master's program, Griffin took courses and participated in his first archaeological fieldwork through excavations at various sites in Illinois, deciding that archaeology rather than other areas of anthropology was his particular area of interest and would serve as the basis for his further study.
Griffin received his master's degree in 1930, then was hired in the summer of 1931 to direct excavations at Athens, Pennsylvania for the Tioga Point Museum under a grant from the National Research Council. He planned to return to Pennsylvania the following year to excavate near Wilkes-Barre, but funding for the project was canceled. In late 1932, Cole put Griffin forward for a fellowship in Aboriginal North American Ceramics administered by the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan with financial support from philanthropist Eli Lilly. The museum's director, Carl Guthe, selected Griffin for the fellowship and he began his pursuit of a doctoral degree in anthropology at Michigan in 1933. Griffin would spend the next fifty years at the university in one role or another.
Griffin's fellowship and work with the Ceramic Repository of the Eastern United States formed the basis for his Ph.D. thesis (completed in 1936) and many of his early publications. The most significant of these was The Fort Ancient Aspect, published by the University of Michigan Press in 1943. Griffin also served as the editor for the important survey publication, Archaeology of Eastern United States (University of Chicago Press, 1952), a festschrift for his mentor, Fay-Cooper Cole.
Griffin worked his way up through the ranks of the Museum of Anthropology, progressing from Research Associate to Assistant Curator to Associate Curator to Curator from 1936 to 1945. In late 1943 Carl Guthe resigned as director of the museum and recommended that Griffin be appointed as his successor. Administrative conflicts stalled the appointment for several years, but he was finally approved by the Regents as the museum's director in 1946. Griffin held this position until his retirement in 1975.
In addition to his work at the museum, Griffin was also very active in the university's Department of Anthropology. He was named Associate Professor in 1945 and promoted to Professor in 1949. He chaired the dissertation committees for more than 40 doctoral students and was an active teacher and advisor. He also served as the department's chair from 1972 to 1975.
Griffin participated in many important initiatives outside the University of Michigan. From 1940 to 1946 (with a break during the war years), Griffin, along with James Ford of Louisiana State and Philip Phillips of Harvard, organized and led the Lower Mississippi Valley Survey. The survey marked one of the first instances of significant inter-institutional cooperation in North American archaeology. Griffin continued his work in the area with the Central Mississippi Valley Archaeological Survey (C.M.V.A.S.), the Cahokia excavations, and the FAI-270 Archaeological Mitigation project.
Griffin was not primarily a field archaeologist, however. His passion and expertise lay in making connections and surmising relationships between different artifacts, geographic areas, sites, and cultures. He was known for his piercing intellect, encyclopedic memory and vast knowledge of the prehistory of North America, externalized in his extensive index cards and pictorial files of ceramics and artifacts. He visited sites throughout the country to collect information and was widely consulted by professional and amateur archaeologists on an array of topics. Throughout his career, Griffin published his own work prolifically, and often reviewed the work of others.
While his primary interest lay in the archaeology of North America, Griffin had many other interests. He traveled extensively, including a year-long study tour of Western Europe from 1953 to 1954 and a research trip to Soviet Russia in 1961, and was involved in initiating some of the earliest field projects for American graduate students behind the "Iron Curtain" in Poland and the former Yugoslavia. Griffin also participated in many regional, national, and international professional organizations, including terms on the leadership boards of the Society for American Archaeology (SAA), the International Union of Prehistoric and Protohistoric Sciences (IUPPS), the American Anthropological Association (AAA), and the Council on Michigan Archaeology (COMA), among others.
Griffin was a pioneer in the development and use of several tools for the scientific analysis of archaeological specimens. Along with H.R. Crane of the university's Department of Physics, Griffin founded and provided oversight for the Radiocarbon Laboratory, in operation at Michigan from 1949 to 1970. The Radiocarbon Laboratory and its program of C-14 dating of specimens was the second of its kind in the United States. In the 1960s, Griffin collaborated with Michigan chemist Adon Gordus in the use of neutron activation analysis for sourcing obsidian, one of the most important analytical tools available to archaeologists for the study of prehistoric exchange. Griffin was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1968 for his innovative scientific work.
After Griffin retired in 1975, he spent a number of years in Ann Arbor as a Research Scientist of the Museum of Anthropology. He then moved to Washington, D.C. in 1984 to serve as a Research Associate of the Smithsonian Institution. He continued to be active in the field of archaeology almost to the very end of his life, attending professional conferences, contributing to publications, and serving as an official or unofficial advisor to scores of younger archaeologists.
Griffin married Ruby Fletcher on February 14, 1936. They were married for over forty years, until her death in 1979. Together they had three sons, John, David, and James. Griffin met his second wife, Mary Marsh DeWitt, while living in Washington. They were together for twelve years, until his death on May 31, 1997, at age 92.
(In addition to the wealth of biographical information that can be found in these papers, there are a number of published biographical resources for James B. Griffin. These include memorials and obituaries published after his death (including "James Bennett Griffin, 1905-97" by Richard I. Ford, published in American Anthropologist in 2002), his entries in reference publications such as Who's Who and the International Directory of Anthropologists, and Griffin's autobiographical essay "An Individual's Participation in American Archaeology, 1928-1985," published in the Annual Review of Anthropology in 1985.)
Summary Contents List
Biographical and Personal -- Box 1
Student Years -- Box 2
Correspondence, 1930-1975 -- Boxes 3-27
Correspondence, 1975-1997 -- Boxes 28-33
Radiocarbon Laboratory Correspondence -- Boxes 34-36 Datasheet Notebooks -- Boxes 36-37 Lab Administration -- Box 37 Research -- Box 37 Card Files -- Boxes 38-48
Teaching and Advising Advising -- Box 49 Courses -- Boxes 49-50 Background Material -- Boxes 50-51 Visiting Teaching Positions -- Boxes 51-52
Conferences and Symposia Professional Organizations and Recurring Conferences -- Boxes 52-58 One-Time Meetings -- Boxes 58-62
Professional Associations and Affiliations -- Boxes 62-65
Speaking Engagements -- Box 65
Travel and International Initiatives -- Boxes 65-66
Writings and Publications By Griffin -- Boxes 66-73 By Others -- Boxes 73-80
Hopewell -- Boxes 81-82
Topical Files Archaeological Subject Files -- Boxes 82-83 Ceramic Research -- Boxes 83-84 Consulting -- Boxes 84-85 Grant Proposals and Projects -- Boxes 85-86 Neutron Activation Analysis -- Box 86 Program Reviews and Evaluations -- Boxes 86-87 University of Michigan -- Box 87
Archaeological Sites and Projects -- Boxes 88-93
North American Archaeology Card Files Geographic Areas and Cultures -- Boxes 94-195 Miscellaneous -- Boxes 196-200 Large Mounted Photographs -- Boxes 201-212 Mississippi Valley Aerial Photographs -- Boxes 213-215
Photographs -- Box 216
The James B. Griffin Papers are a rich source of information about Griffin's life, the history of the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan, archaeological sites and topics, particularly in North America, and the overall development of the field of North American archaeology from the 1930s to the 1990s. The papers consist of 16 series: Biographical and Personal; Student Years; Correspondence, 1930-1975; Correspondence, 1975-1997; Radiocarbon Laboratory; Teaching and Advising; Conferences and Symposia; Professional Associations and Affiliations; Speaking Engagements; Travel and International Initiatives; Writings and Publications; Hopewell; Topical Files; Archaeological Sites and Projects; North American Archaeology Card Files; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Anthropology--Study and teaching.; Anthropology--History.; Pottery--Analysis.; Hopewell culture.; Mississippian culture.; Radiocarbon dating.; Indians of North America--Antiquities.; Excavations (Archaeology)--North America.; Fort Ancient culture.; Cahokia Mounds State Historic Park (Ill.); American Bottom (Ill.)--Antiquities.; Illinois--Antiquities.; Ohio--Antiquities.; Michigan--Antiquities.; Missouri--Antiquities.; United States--Antiquities.; North America--Antiquities.; Mississippi River Valley--Antiquities.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Griffin, James B. (James Bennett), 1905-1997; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan. Radiocarbon Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Archaeology.; Anthropology.; Pottery.; Hopewell culture.; Mississippian culture.; Fort Ancient culture.; Indians of North America--Antiquities.; Excavations (Archaeology)--North America.; Cahokia Mounds State Historic Park (Ill.); American Bottom (Ill.)--Antiquities.; Illinois--Antiquities.; Ohio--Antiquities.; Michigan--Antiquities.; Missouri--Antiquities.; United States--Antiquities.; North America--Antiquities.; Mississippi River Valley--Antiquities.
Contributors:
Griffin, James B. (James Bennett), 1905-1997; Williams, Stephen, 1926-; Ford, James Alfred, 1911-1968.; Phillips, Philip, 1900-1994; Cole, Fay-Cooper, b. 1881.; Morgan, Richard Guy, 1903-; Rouse, Irving, 1913-2006; Greber, N'omi.; Spaulding, Albert C. (Albert Clanton), 1914-1990; Guthe, Carl E. (Carl Eugen), 1893-1974; Lilly, Eli, 1885-1977; Morse, Dan F.; Stephenson, Robert L. (Robert Lloyd), 1919-; MacNeish, Richard S.; Jennings, Jesse D. (Jesse David), 1909-1997; Black, Glenn A. (Glenn Albert), 1900-1964.; Chapman, Carl H. (Carl Haley), 1915-1987; Eggan, Fred, 1906-1991; Titterington, Paul Francis, 1895-1969.; Willey, Gordon R. (Gordon Randolph), 1913-2002; Drooker, Penelope B.; Roosevelt, Anna Curtenius.; Krieger, Alex D. (Alex Dony), 1911-1991; Perino, Gregory.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan. Radiocarbon Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Society for American Archaeology.; American Anthropological Association.; Southeastern Archaeological Conference.; International Union of Prehistoric and Protohistoric Sciences.; Conference on Michigan Archaeology.; Central Mississippi Valley Archaeological Survey.; Lower Mississippi Survey.; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.). Anthropology Section.; Ceramic Repository for the Eastern United States.
Genre/Form:
Field notes.; Photographs.
- Biographical and Personal, 1933-1988
  The Biographical and Personal series, 1933-1988 (1 linear foot), contains Griffin's curriculum vitae, biographical and bibliographical information submitted to various publications, a set of appointment calendars, and other personal information. Of particular note are the folders of newspaper clippings, which provide a comprehensive record of press coverage of Griffin and selected articles on the field of archaeology during his career.
  - Appointment Calendars
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Birth Record, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Biography and Bibliography, 1948-1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Certificates and Citations (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
  - Faculty Personnel Record, 1945-1972 (Box 1)
  - Family History (Box 1)
  - Membership and Identification Cards (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Passports, 1950s-1970s (Box 1)
  - Sale of Library, 1980-1988; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - U-M Appointment Terms, 1933-1990 (Box 1)
  - Weather Readings for Chicago, 1862-1876 (Box 1)
    (ledger that may have belonged to a relative of Griffin, possibly his great-grandfather, Joseph Bennett)
- Student Years, 1922-1936
  The Student Years series, 1922-1936 (1 linear foot), consists primarily of course notes, papers, examinations, and project background research from Griffin's time as a graduate student in the master's degree program in anthropology at the University of Chicago. The series also includes a small amount of material related to Griffin's high school studies, undergraduate degree (also received from the University of Chicago) and doctoral program (at U-M), as well as one folder of correspondence. The folders titled "Anthropology at American Universities" and "History of Anthropology" contain research Griffin conducted while he was a student on the early development of the field, and include letters from representatives of anthropology departments around the United States.
  - Courses
    - American Indian, 1929 (Box 2)
    - Ancient and Medieval American History (taught by Carl Guthe), 1933 (Box 2)
    - Anthropology 280 (General Introduction to Anthropology), 1926 (Box 2)
    - Course Outlines, undated (Box 2)
    - Cultural Anthropology, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Cultural Evolution (taught by Leslie White), 1933 (Box 2)
    - Ethnology, 1927
    - Examination Questions, 1926-1936 (Box 2)
    - Historical Geology, 1929 (Box 2)
    - History 141, 1933 (Box 2)
    - Linguistics, Phonetics, Psychology of Culture, and Psychology of Primitive Religions (all taught by Edward Sapir), 1928-1932 (Box 2)
    - North American Archaeology (taught by Carl Guthe), 1933 (Box 2)
    - Peoples of the South Pacific, Ethnology of Malaysia, and Peoples of the World (all taught by Fay-Cooper Cole), 1928-? (Box 2)
    - Present Day Mexico, Ethnography of Middle America, and Primitive Society (all taught by Robert Redfield), 1929-1934 (Box 2)
    - Regional Geography of the United States, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Social Origins, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Projects and Papers
    - Anthropology at American Universities, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 2)
    - Bibliography of American Indian Medicine and Medicine Men, [1932] (Box 2)
    - History of Anthropology, undated (Box 2)
    - "Ludendorff's Own Story - A Review,", undated (Box 2)
    - Malaysia and the South Pacific, 1930 (Box 2)
    - Medicine and Magic
      - Northeast Woodlands, undated (Box 2)
      - Plains Indians, undated (Box 2)
      - Southeast Woodlands, undated (Box 2)
    - Physical Anthropology and American Indian Pathology, undated (Box 2)
    - "A Presentation of Ethnological Ideologies,", undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Commencement Program (U-M), 1936 (Box 2)
    - Convocation Program (U. Chicago), 1927 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1936 (Box 2)
      (includes telegram from Carl Guthe informing Griffin of U-M fellowship)
    - High School, 1922 (Box 2)
      (includes report cards and yearbook entry)
    - Honors Convocation Programs (U-M), 1933-1934 (Box 2)
    - List of Degrees in Anthropology Granted by American Institutions, 1927-1933 (Box 2)
    - Master of Arts Diploma, 1930 (Box 2)
    - Notebook (includes poems and list of plays Griffin saw), 1920s (Box 2)
    - Phi Sigma, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
    - Sigma Xi, 1931-1936 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1930-1975
  The Correspondence, 1930-1975 series (25 linear feet) contains Griffin's incoming and outgoing personal and professional correspondence during the most active years of his professional career. The series is incredibly rich as Griffin corresponded with nearly all of the prominent figures in North American archaeology of his time. The series includes not only letters, postcards, and telegrams, but also drafts of articles, reports from field sites, maps, and photographs of people and objects (more comprehensive documentation on particular archaeological sites, photographs, and extensive publication files can be elsewhere in the papers). The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with any supplemental material from a particular correspondent filed together with his or her letters. While most of the correspondence, including all with regular correspondents, is arranged in individual folders by the name of the correspondent, correspondence with infrequent correspondents and some routine correspondence is collected alphabetically in the "Miscellaneous" folders at the end of each letter range.
  The series represents all phases of Griffin's pre-retirement professional career. Early correspondence includes letters to and from Griffin's mentors, most notably Fay-Cooper Cole and Carl Guthe. Later correspondence shows Griffin as a mentor and advisor himself, to students and junior colleagues including Gregory Perino, Stephen Williams, Jeffrey Parsons, Wesley Hurt, Clifford Evans, Betty Meggers, and Dan Morse. Correspondence with Griffin's contemporaries figures prominently throughout the series, and provides insight into his long-term associations with Irving Rouse, J.O. Brew, Emil Haury, Gordon Willey, Charles Fairbanks, Philip Phillips, Richard MacNeish, Jesse Jennings, and Fred Eggan, among many others. Griffin's correspondents spanned all of North America, and included Mexican archaeologists such as Eduardo Noguera, Pedro Armillas, and Ignacio Marquina, and Canadians such as William E. Taylor and J. Norman Emerson.
  Correspondence with Griffin's University of Michigan colleagues, including museum curators and administrators Carl Guthe, Albert Spaulding, Kamer Aga-Oglu, Richard Ford, and Volney Jones, and Department of Anthropology heads Leslie White and J.N. Spuhler, is well represented in the series. The Museum's evolving status at the University of Michigan can be seen in discussions with university administrators such as College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) deans Alfred Sussman, Ralph Sawyer, and William Haber, and executive officers such as Secretary of the University Herbert Watkins and Assistant to the President Erich Walter. Correspondence from Griffin to his secretary at the museum during his leave year in London from 1953-1954 and during a summer project in 1952 provides insight into his activities while away from the museum, as other museum curators' correspondence to him from the field provides insight into theirs.
  Griffin's correspondence documents not only individual personalities and research in North American archaeology, but also broader themes in the field. Griffin's extensive correspondence with his early patron Eli Lilly, and proposals to major sources of funding for anthropology, including the Wenner-Gren Foundation (as found particularly in the correspondence with Paul Fejos) and the National Science Foundation, demonstrate the crucial role outside financial support played in the development of the archaeological field. While Griffin corresponded regularly with a number of amateur archaeologists and received volumes of inquiries from avocationalists throughout his career, like many of his academic peers, he was also very concerned with the professionalization of archaeology. Griffin was one of the original 31 signers of the constitution of the Society for American Archaeology and served as an officer from 1945 to 1956 (including a term as president in 1951), and his correspondence with fellow officers and members demonstrates the growth of this important professional association.
  While most notable for its documentation of the field of North American archaeology, the Correspondence, 1930-1975 series also contains materials that illustrate and provide insight into key events and trends in American history. Correspondence from the 1930s includes letters from a number of people working for the Works Progress Administration (WPA), a key source of funding for North American archaeology in its formative years. Parallels with the early Cold War crusades of the House Un-American Activities Committee can be seen in the case of James Griffin's friend, Richard G. Morgan, who was fired from the Ohio State Museum (and effectively exiled from the academic field of anthropology) in 1948 for his purported ties to the Communist Party. Correspondence from this time period between Griffin and Morgan, as well as with John W. Bennett and Fay-Cooper Cole, provides insight into the specifics of the case and the American Anthropological Association's (AAA) intervention on Morgan's behalf.
  - Abelson, Philip H., 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Aberle, David F., 1954-1968 (Box 3)
  - Accounting Department, 1955-1971 (Box 3)